Thank you, young man.
Now, I'll need something for headache.
Oil of hemlock.
And some sumac berry syrup.
Oh, and some blackberry root tea leaves.
Sounds as if the household's down with
the influenza, Janet.
Don't say that, Alvaro. We have far too
much lambing left to do to fall ill.
No, no, it's just precautionary.
Well, the pharmacopoeia would suggest
sweet fern.
Sweet fern.
All right.
Yes, and persimmon tea.
Thanks, Elvira.
Oh!
Oh, good Lord!
Great Aunt Eliza!
What a surprise!
I should have known you wouldn't be on
time, dilly -dallying with the gossip.
Well, now, dear, you should have
written. We had no idea.
No need to patronize me, Janet.
I did write.
You won't fool me into not coming just
because you didn't write me that.
And heaven of those bags!
Gently, take it gently.
Oh, Alex was supposed to come and pick
me up.
Honestly, Aunt Eliza, we didn't get your
letter. We never received a single
word. Now, perhaps you... Perhaps I may
be getting on in years, but I should be
able to recollect that I wrote to you.
Oh, Janet, please don't leave me out
here. I shall catch my death.
Whatever you say, Aunt Eliza.
I don't know why you insist on keeping
this old buggy. It's falling apart at
joints.
Yes.
Great Aunt Eliza.
Come on.
These ewes will be ready to give birth
any day. Yoo -hoo!
Hattie! Alex! Children!
Come and say hello to Aunt Eliza.
What did she say?
Greetings, Eliza.
Here today?
Oh, good Lord.
Come along now, children. Must at least
be cordial.
Here we go, dear.
Oh, I don't know if I can move. My back
is in a hundred pieces.
Buzzing.
Hard to see.
Oh. Oh,
no, no, no. I'm chilled to the bone.
Had a pleasant trip then, Eliza?
Hallie King.
Well, I can see your age has certainly
caught up to you since my last short
visit.
It's amazing how you never change,
Eliza. But you should have written. I
we're really not prepared to have you
stay here.
I did write, as I told Janet.
It's not my fault if my letter has got
displaced amongst all this clutter and
chaos.
Still not able to manage a household,
Janet dear.
Felix is just bringing in the last of
the bags.
Where should we put them all, Mother
dear?
Oh, unprepared as usual, Janet.
Always in a fluster.
Tell me, child, which is the warmest
room in this house?
The kitchen.
I mean the warmest bedroom.
Hello, Felix.
Haven't grown much taller, have you?
Hello, great Aunt Eliza. The warmest
bedroom really would be the boys' room.
What? Well, then, take my things up to
the boys' room.
Daniel can stay in our room.
Yes, very good, very good, dear.
Felix, you'll just have to stay
downstairs for a while. Oh, please,
me.
How long will you be staying, Aunt
Eliza? Oh.
Oh, not long, dear, I'm sure.
A month, two months.
Oh, who can say how much longer I am
intended to be on this earth, for
sake.
Yes. Well, now I must go up and test
that mattress.
Come along, Peter. I can't manage those
dreadful hairs on my own.
Getting settled in, dear?
This is an awfully cold house, Janet.
Oh, well, I've just put some more wood
on, Aunt Liza. Give it time.
Time.
That's all there is in the end.
One knows when one's time is up, Janet.
Oh.
What?
What did you say exactly?
She said, in the end, time is all we
have.
But what did she mean? She wouldn't say.
Well, I didn't ask, but I'm dreadfully
afraid she's come here.
Well, I mean, perhaps she's... Oh, I
don't know. Maybe I should write to
Abigail. Oh, she seems fit as a fiddle
to me.
For certain, that tongue of hers has
never been sharper.
Alec, I think we should be especially
kind to her.
Agreed.
But why us? Why now?
In the middle of lambing season, all
these animals ready to give birth.
Who can say after all the... Oh, my
goodness.
You work in mysterious ways.
Alec, here it comes.
Leave it.
Stir yourself, boy. Come along.
What's the matter?
I need water for my tea.
Is it morning?
No, it certainly isn't. It's just past
midnight.
I can see dull witness runs in your
family. Now, come along.
have tea, Great Aunt Eliza. Not
satisfactory for this time of the year.
You all may wish to suffer the
influenza, but I do not.
Felix, the stove is out on embers.
We used all of the firewood already. I'd
have to go with fine.
But four or five pieces will suffice,
Felix.
Goodness, Great Aunt Eliza.
At this rate, I won't get any sleep.
It's just my mother.
I am here, and I'm asking you, Felix.
It seems to me like you've been asking
me a lot of things lately.
And it doesn't seem to me why you can't
just go and get what you want yourself.
Your parents will hear of this, Felix.
Wait, wait.
I'll get the wood.
Rise and shine, Felix. You've got plenty
of work ahead of us today.
Laura had a full night of work.
What do you mean?
First it was water for her tea, then
wood for the stove, another blanket,
open the window, no, close the window,
then a hot water bottle for her feet.
Oh, buck off, Felix.
Mother, I can't get any sleep down here.
Great Aunt Eliza. Darling, she's
elderly.
Will you try to understand?
I'm off to the barn.
Well, without any breakfast, Eric.
No, I don't feel too hungry, you know.
Stomach's not an uneven keel. Oh, well,
I'll bring you out something special.
I feel battleaxe now.
Felix King, I should wash your mouth out
with soap, and I told you to be kind to
your great Aunt Eliza.
I hope I don't get that old feeble.
Good morning, Aunt Eliza. Isn't it a
fine day?
I should hardly say so, Janet. My feet
are like blocks of ice. Oh.
Really, you and Alec are so skimpy with
the heating in this place.
Pillows are as hard as rock.
I've got a crick in my neck. I didn't
sleep well at all.
Oh, I'm so sorry, dear.
Now, Janet, there are a few things I
need.
I don't think that it will inconvenience
you at all.
It's because of my rheumatism.
Yes, dear.
I have one egg each and every day. In
case you don't remember, your memory
was very good.
One three -minute egg and a piece of dry
toast, tea, very hot
rosehip. Yes. Well, I'm not quite sure
about the rosehip.
Oh, what about you, Janet?
If you could, will you refill this hot
water bucket? Yes, of course.
Janet, what are you waiting for?
Oh, nothing.
So,
we
can conclude, as did Sir Isaac Newton,
that light is made of a mixture of
different colours forming the optical
spectrum.
You have a question, Mr. King.
Uh, yes.
If light is white, how can it be
colored?
Through the separation of its particles.
Yes, particles. But if there's a bunch
of particles, why can't we see them?
Quiet. It's a legitimate question.
Miss King, you have an answer, perhaps.
Isaac Newton investigated the optical
spectrum and established a theory of
based on a hypothesis that light is
composed of a stream of particles that
disturb the area around them. That is
precisely his theory, Miss King. Yes,
light is light, like a sun or a candle.
I can see that. I can see light.
And when the light goes out, it's dark.
So how come anybody can say...
That these so -called particles exist
when we can't even see them.
Well, Mr. King, to paraphrase
Shakespeare, there are many things that
the world that aren't dreamt of in your
philosophy.
Science has offered us great
advancements in the last 25 years and is
of the future.
Your future.
I shall expect the science project on
one of the following subjects to be
presented in a week's time.
You may work in teams.
You will state an hypothesis, conduct
the experiment, and submit your
conclusions.
There will be a prize for the best
project, and your grade will be worth 50
your science mark.
Properties of light, wave theory,
combustion engine, electricity.
I have enough to do with the old
subjects without all the science.
Cram it all into your head for the
examinations and then forget it?
That's hardly an attitude of someone
likely to succeed in life, Felix.
School has nothing to do with life,
Felicity.
Well, I'm sure I haven't the head for
scientific theory.
Oh, phooey on it.
They discover something one day, just
have someone else say it's different the
next. I'll discover something myself.
I have a feeling your imagination is
running away with you now, Felix.
You're just jealous, Felicity, because
you don't have a creative bone in your
body. I have enough creativity to
imagine my future life without you.
I hate those snails.
Coming right up.
I could use something hot to drink.
You look kind of sore today, Alec.
What's the matter?
Well, I... Well, where's your brother?
Mrs. Lawson had a delivery for Uncle
Jasper, so Sarah and Felix are just
it over to the Dale house and then
they'll be home.
You look feverish.
It's nothing.
Seamus came while Jasper's away.
He wanted us to just leave it here and
not fiddle with it. I swear, it doesn't
weigh anything.
What could Uncle Jasper have been
working on recently?
And what could be in a box that weighs
almost nothing?
Felix, don't fiddle with it.
A light bulb.
Dozens of light bulbs.
Electricity on Prince Edward Island?
It'll be just like Montreal.
You know, Sarah,
If we look through Uncle Jasper's notes,
we could probably come up with the best
science project of the year.
Aunt Hattie's already at the barn.
Hurry up, Felix. We're supposed to be
helping.
Oh, for pity's sake.
I'm coming.
Tell me if my mother comes back.
Pretty clever, eh?
Felix shall freeze.
Survival of the fittest.
I've learned a lot of things at school
besides science.
Come on, we'd better hurry to Uncle
Jasper's and be back for the lambing
they miss us.
with the sheep, no doubt.
Thank you, Daniel.
You know you are a very lucky little
boy, Daniel King.
You have a wonderful large family around
you.
Oh, Daniel.
You're quite feverish.
Aunt Eliza, is Daniel bothering you? Do
you need something?
Oh, never mind. I'm not important.
But really, Janet, I had hoped you'd
gain some sense over the years.
Whatever do you mean, dear? It's a
wonder to me that any of your children
still living and breathing.
I'm sure I don't know what you're
talking about, Aunt Eliza. Well, this
here is burning up with fever.
What?
Influenza, I say.
Caused, no doubt, by the extreme damp in
this drafty old farmhouse.
There's absolutely nothing wrong with
this house, Aunt Eliza. Oh, I...
Have you ever noticed anything at all,
Janice? You're always in such a muddle.
Oh, yes, I know. So you keep telling me.
Well, there's absolutely nothing the
matter with Daniel either. He's just
overheated us all.
He just needs some fresh air.
See, the bicycle somehow creates enough
power to make the electricity work.
Bicycle? I don't get it.
Neither do I, really.
But that's what it says here, I think.
an invisible power that picked me up and
threw me across the room. Well, you
know better than to go into Jasper's
workshop when he's not there.
I not butter Janet.
Hetty is correct.
Plying into someone else's private
things when they're not at home.
Really. Uncle Jasper allows us in his
workshop.
And you're always telling us to be more
independent and resourceful, so we were.
There's surely a difference between
being resourceful and life...
You should go to your room, Felix.
I don't have a room, remember?
I don't need any smart remarks right
now. Go to the barn, and that's where
you're supposed to be helping.
Like I've been hit by a train.
Well, Alec, I'll make you some
blackberry root tea.
What did I tell you?
Influenza. I was very curious at your
age, Alec.
I remember my cousin Alice went to bed
in perfect health.
The next morning, her mother went in,
and there she lay, her elegant fingers
gripping the sheets, her eyes fixed, and
her mouth open in a last gasp.
That's enough, Eliza. Can't you see
you're upsetting the whole household
these prophecies of doom?
Look, I'm sorry.
I understand.
I'll just go back to my room. All this
exertion down here, very trying, Eliza.
age. Who knows?
I may die in my sleep like Uncle Robert.
Alec, I really think you should stay in
bed tomorrow.
Oh, and let the children take care of
the lambing?
Father, we've helped with lambing many
times.
Besides, this could be the last time I'm
even part of the lambing.
What with the possibility of school away
next year. Yeah, but, Alec, I'm sure
that with the children helping, Hetty
and I can manage.
Well, not with great Aunt Eliza needing
your constant attention.
Besides, a little hard work is just the
ticket to what ails me.
I just know I'm going to have problems
with those new ewes. I can feel it in my
bones.
Oh, this smells as bad as that last
concoction. What was it, oil of hemlock?
Well, you just try it.
I can't, Janet. It makes me gag.
Now, I know you don't want me to
interfere, Alec, but I really do feel
have something in here.
Look, I don't want to know about any new
remedies. I don't care. I'm going to
bed.
You brought this influenza on your whole
household, Janet.
You were never one to take precautionary
measures or think something through.
Oh, live for today, we reap what we sow.
You were too busy counting sheep, I dare
say, to take notice of your alien land.
Yes, Aunt Eliza, I'm sure you know all
about it. You've had so many children of
your own.
Felicity, you'll go blind if you
continue to read by lamplight.
Yes, Great Aunt Eliza.
You seem to take after your Aunt Hetty.
You have that... Pinched look, just like
the rest of the King family.
Janet!
Great Aunt Eliza, what's wrong?
Oh, this room is as cold as an igloo.
I'll fetch another blanket.
It'll take a few minutes to know.
Why don't you sit down here and we can
have a little chat until I get warmed
What do you mean by pinched? You always
seem such a serious, down -hearted
child. Oh, it's nothing.
I know I must seem like a doddering old
woman to you, but I was a young girl
once. Would you be kind enough to plump
up these pillows for me?
You know...
It's my experience that when a young
girl is preoccupied, the cause is
matter of love.
No, not really.
Well, maybe partly.
That and graduating soon.
Perhaps going away.
It's just that why can't things stay as
they are?
There are so many decisions.
But how do I know which is the right
one?
You must weigh your present against the
possibilities of your future.
But I don't know about my future.
I was always a headstrong and
opinionated young girl when I was young.
Much like yourself.
On a holiday in New York with my cousin
Louise, I met and fell in love with a
young Union soldier, Lyle Prescott.
It was all very sudden.
He wanted to marry me before going back
to his regiment.
But you didn't.
No, I didn't.
I was afraid.
Afraid of losing my family, my friends,
my home.
I was afraid of the future.
My heart said yes to Captain Prescott.
But I said no.
And I turned my back on a possible road
of my life.
Who knows?
I might have had a family.
A daughter like you, Felicity.
But you didn't know you wouldn't get
another chance, Great Aunt Eliza.
No.
I held back and became trapped in the
moment of time.
Life can be very, very long, my dear.
You should do what your heart tells you
to do.
No matter whatever people say.
Good night, Green Antelosa.
Good night, Felicity, dear.
There, there, my fine soldier boy. We'll
soon have you feeling better.
None of that nasty brew of your
mother's. We have some nice water ravens
for you. Indian chocolate to bring your
fever down. Make you feel better.
Did you say chocolate?
Indian chocolate.
So we used to call water ravens.
Nobody remembers it now. Your parents
don't want to listen to an old lady like
me. But what was all that about
chocolate?
Well, it tastes like chocolate.
Hence its English name.
Say, this is great, hmm?
There's a good boy.
Now, you must have some fluids along
with the medicine.
Where'd you ever learn about that? Oh,
well, my mother was a great believer in
native medicine.
You know, the Micmacs used this plant,
water ravens, to cure the influenza.
Maybe father should have a drink of
that.
He should, no doubt.
But what do I know?
I'm just part of the past, Felix.
Don't let me keep you up, boy. I've just
stopped by to tend the little one. And
I know you have a man's work to do
tomorrow.
That's all right.
No, I was decidedly selfish to you the
other night, and it hasn't made any
difference. That room is still freezing.
Great -aunt Eliza, there's something I
think you should know.
And what would that be, Felix?
I, uh, turned the heat off to your room.
I'm sorry.
I'm not at all surprised.
You're a very clever boy.
It's just like whenever I think of
something, it causes no end of trouble
disaster.
You shouldn't let people dissuade you
from discovering what you want to for
yourself, Felix.
After all, where would one get in the
world if you didn't charge ahead?
Oh, there'll be bumps and bruises on the
way, but what can you expect?
You have great spirit.
And an imagination when it suits your
purpose.
I suppose.
Great Aunt Eliza.
I think you might want to sleep down
here.
It's warmer and I'll take my room.
That's very considerate of you, Felix.
I'll bring down your things and your
blankets and your pillow.
Thank you, Felix.
Take me, Taylor.
No.
Boiled bark of white oak.
Press him in tea, perhaps?
I think those remedies are making me
worse, Janet.
But I'll, uh... I'll be all right once I
get out to the barn. Work's the best
remedy.
You look all in, too.
First you, then Daniel.
Great Aunt Eliza doesn't give me a
moment's rest.
She's completely disrupted the
household.
Felix mopes about the house all day
because he doesn't get any sleep at
Her nocturnal wanderings are making it
impossible for me to sleep as well.
Nothing is good enough for her.
Certainly, I am not good enough for her.
Tried to make me feel you would even as
a girl.
I know, I know.
Well, you're just going to have to talk
to her, Janet.
What am I going to say?
Oh, don't warn her, Frazzle. My thinking
is that we put her on the first train
to Avid Hills until we finish the
lambing. At least we get a good night's
I can't turn her out.
Look, you're not turning her out.
Abigail's her relation as much as you
are. In fact, her family, well, they
should be informed about her condition.
Maybe we should consider a hospital for
some kind of treatment. I don't know,
but we can't continue to live like this.
I know.
Why did you come here?
She really doesn't like me very much.
She never has come.
Oh, we traded places last night.
She was too cold for her.
Where are her things?
I must go to the doctor's as well.
Oh, no.
Oh, no, oh, no, no, no.
Look, Daniel.
A lamb's bottle.
Eddie,
have you seen Eliza?
Delilah switched beds with Felix last
night, and she overheard Alec and I
talking about her. Now she's packed up
and gone.
Oh, my.
Oh, I am not surprised.
She always was a free -minded woman.
We said such terrible things about her.
She's always so...
Critical and overbearing.
Never a kind word about me. Never.
Janet, did it never occur to you that
being critical and overbearing, as you
it, may be her way of trying to be more
involved with you and the family? I
know. I know. She was the only one who
dared stand up to that father of yours.
Why, if it hadn't been for great Aunt
Eliza, he'd never have relented and
allowed you to marry Alec.
I didn't know that.
Why would she have done that for me?
I suppose she knew Alec was what your
heart desired.
Well, heaven knows why.
Oh, Eddie.
It's true.
Now, I thrust her out into the cold.
And she came here for comfort in her old
age.
Eddie, can you look after Daniel?
I'm going to go after Eliza.
I'm afraid it's just too
cold for them to survive.
There must be something else we can do.
Well, we can move them all in closer
together. That should save two or three
them.
Sarah,
run and fetch Arthur Pettibone, will
you? Please, he can help us.
Keep your coat done up.
Sarah Stanley.
Is Arthur at home?
We have an emergency with our lambs at
the King Bar.
I'm afraid he's off to Nova Scotia.
Everyone's afraid that the lambs will
die in this cold snap.
Hang on, Sarah. I'll be with you in a
second.
I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry.
You were so sophisticated.
You knew everything.
I'm here. I was such a disappointment.
Suppose that way we could save one or
two.
Helix, what temperature is it?
Minus ten.
It's frozen.
Alec, it's frozen.
We just can't generate enough heat for
them or for ourselves.
How can we get more heat?
Heat is... heat's energy.
What?
Like when you jump up and down and get
warm.
Please, children, I know you're trying
to help, but really, jumping up and down
is not very realistic.
We'll just do our best to save a few of
them.
I think I should run and get the doctor.
She seems so gray and demented from the
cold.
Her cases, Alec. That's what she wants
out of the buggy. Could you get them for
her?
Yes, dear.
Yes, dear. Hetty and Alec will get them
for you.
Old,
frail, and sick.
That's what we all have to look forward
to, Hetty. Oh, no, Alec. She's not dead
yet. Well, it always seems the same.
I remember our parents, you know.
Salt of the earth, kind, caring people
who became cantankerous and critical,
just like Eliza. I hate remembering them
that way. Oh, perhaps you're afraid.
One day you may become just what you
fear the most.
Well, look what a bout of influenza does
to my constitution and temperament.
Well, the truth is, Eliza has some quite
useful information, if you'll listen
for me.
You just won't listen.
I can't even save my own lambs. I'm too
ill to think straight.
I have to leave it all to the children,
for heaven's sakes, to Felix.
And what's wrong with that? There's
nothing whatever the matter with letting
children, even Felix, take care of
lambing for you.
You just can't face their becoming
independent, that's all, with minds of
own.
You were once, once upon a time, just
like them, you know.
Now, come on.
Are you sure you're all right, ma 'am?
I'm going to be fine.
Just do stop hovering. Oh, yes.
Of course.
Thank you, Patty.
Does this look fine to you? No, not at
all.
I want something to be warm all over.
I want some of these. Where are they?
This.
This. This.
Portrait.
Can you make this up?
Into a tea idea?
Absolutely. Can you manage here?
Oh, yes, of course. I'll help you go.
Here's the lamb.
Thank you. Thank you.
What in heaven's name is going on here?
We're making heat, Father.
Aren't they just beautiful?
Aunt Hattie, just listen to us for a
minute.
You see, you pedal that bicycle.
And it makes the generator work.
And the current flows through these
wires into these black boxes here. And
sends power to the light bulbs.
This is ingenious.
All set, I hope.
Mr. Pettibone, could you please pedal
that bicycle?
You're going to have to pedal a lot
faster than that, Mr. Pettibone.
Well,
I'll be.
It's the heat of the sun in the height
of summer.
Quickly, go and tell your mother and
great aunt Eliza. Pitch them down here.
It's warm.
Great Aunt Eliza.
You gave me such a fright.
Really, Janet.
I am perfectly capable of taking care of
myself most of the time.
Yes, you are. You always have been.
I'm sorry.
I am a very forthright, overbearing
woman.
But, oh, Janet.
My feet are blocks of ice.
And it chills right up into my bones.
Aunt Janet, Father says to bring Great
Aunt Eliza down to the barn.
The barn?
Felix and I have created heat.
Sarah and Felix have displayed
initiative and a dramatic understanding
scientific principles.
You could well take home the prize.
Certainly a very high mark in science.
Yes, I was wrong.
School is an important part of life.
I have to agree with you there, son.
This is wonderful.
Felix, however did you get this idea?
I wouldn't have, except for great Aunt
Eliza.
Like all the ward women, you are a
wonder.
Oh, I can hardly believe this nonsense.
But the heat suits me.
Dear Aunt Eliza, can you ever forgive
me?
But what was all that about?
Your time being up.
I didn't mean that, Janet.
Oh, we wards, we're not susceptible to
illnesses.
No, it's just that I feel all my old
friends are gone.
And sometimes I just feel so alone and
quite... Well,
dear, great Aunt Eliza, you're welcome
here any time.
For as long as you like.